Contact

9560102391 (Home) kapilgupta.pt@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/kapil-kumargupta (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Data Lakes aws data lake Amazon Web Services (AWS)

Certifications

Global Certificate in Data Science
Al Infrastructure and Operations
Fundamentals

Software Processes and Agile Practices

Introduction to Software Product Management

Architecting Solutions on AWS

Kapil Kumar Gupta

Al & Cloud Automation | Edge Computing | Al-Driven GTM Strategy | Speaker & Thought Leader

Bengaluru, Karnataka, India

Summary

Technology Leader | Al & Cloud Automation | Thought Leader & GTM Strategist

I am a technology and product leader with 14+ years of experience driving cloud automation, cloud-native architectures, and edge-computing innovations. My passion lies in leveraging AI, GenAI, and cloud automation to optimize network operations, predictive analytics, and multi-cloud infrastructure.

Key Areas of Expertise:

AI & Cloud Strategy: Developing AI-driven cloud transformation strategies, aligning AI/ML automation with business goals.

Cloud & Al Automation: Edge cloud Automation, self-healing Kubernetes, workload orchestration

Al-Enhanced Cloud Operations: Leveraging GenAl and LLMs for predictive maintenance, self-healing infrastructure, and automation.

Thought Leadership: Writing Al/cloud articles, contributing to industry discussions, expanding influence in Al-driven automation # Speaking Engagements & Conference Talks: Actively seeking opportunities to present Al-driven cloud automation strategies

To know more about me, use chatbot: https://huggingface.co/spaces/kapilguptapt/_CareersConversion

I am currently writing thought leadership articles on LinkedIn, contributing to Al/cloud discussions, and planning to engage in speaking opportunities at key industry conferences.

If you're interested in Al-powered cloud automation, GTM strategies, or thought leadership collaboration, let's connect!

DM me or connect to discuss AI in cloud, automation, and business strategy!

Experience

Radisys

5 years 1 month

Senior Architect

August 2024 - Present (1 year 1 month)

Bengaluru, Karnataka, India

Product Owner and Architect for ECP platform and Network Automation.

Presented AI & cloud automation strategy to CXOs, influencing GTM roadmap Championed AI-driven cloud automation, reducing operational costs & improving efficiency

Engaged in pre-sales & solution discussions for cloud offerings

Architect

February 2023 - July 2024 (1 year 6 months)

Bengaluru, Karnataka, India

Working Product Owner to build the Edge computing platform and network Automation

Technical Specialist

August 2020 - January 2023 (2 years 6 months)

Bengaluru, Karnataka, India

Working as Architect to develop strategies and architecture for edge and Multi access edge computing (MEC) that include high-performance edge computing using K8s, distributed cloud deployment for MEC, O-RAN, Automation, Edge AI/ML, CI/CD.

- Product Owner to lead the Global Scrum team to deliver edge computing and automation.
- Collaborate with domain, product management, and product engineering teams in solution engineering efforts and provide architectural guidance to cross-functional teams throughout the program lifecycle.
- Led solution designing, planning, CXO presenting, selection strategy and development for cloud platform from scratch.
- Active participation to response RFP/RFI for Edge cloud solutions for different customers with presales.
- Leading solution architecture from pre-sales to field deployment for Tier-1/2 customers across the globe primarily focusing on Edge/Cloud/NFV/5G/FTTH domains.

- Product Owner and solution architect for Global scrum team to develop the Edge computing platform and zero-touch automation and engage stakeholders proactively and ensure successful project outcomes.
- Lead and oversee the end-to-end IT architecture for Edge, and Cloud solutions, collaborating with internal and external partners.
- Design the Backup and restore, resilience, and Monitoring for Edge clouds.
- Develop strategies and architecture for Multi access edge computing (MEC) that's include high performance edge compute using K8s, distributed cloud deployment for MEC, O-RAN, 5G core, Traffic steering, Automation, Edge AI/ML, CI/CD.
- Studying next generation technologies, conceptualizing, and prototyping solutions.
- Built team for Cloud and DevOps experts to build high performance telco cloud for O-RAN, MEC and 5G apps.
- Create testcases to evaluate the multiple cloud platform.
- Responsible to lead the discussion with partners and cross team stakeholders.
- Design solution for logging & monitoring and implement cloud platform security.

Rakuten India Senior Technical Lead December 2018 - July 2020 (1 year 8 months) Bangaon Area, India

RCCP Cloud-Native Kubernetes cluster design and deployment for production for vRAN and MEC applications using Enhance performance awareness EPA (SRIOV, Multus, NUMA node, CPU pinning, HugePages).

Led distributed Cloud monitoring, hierarchical dashboards, and alarms enrichment & co-relation across the network that includes more than 4000 data centers (Edge and central sites). And implement HW monitoring using IPMI. Technology stack Prometheus, Kafka, Collected, Graphana, ELK.

Led Rakuten mobile network FUT launch to ensure all 100+ datacenters integration with OSS for FCAPS.

Build logic to manage very large data from 4000 Edge site to display NFVi KPI's metrics with near real time.

HCL Technologies
Technical Lead, ERS[Engineering and R&D services]

April 2016 - December 2018 (2 years 9 months)

Noida

- 1.OpenStack, Kubernetes, VMware Cloud deployment and openation using SRE approach
- 2 ONAP lab design & deployment on OpenStack as well as on VIO(VMware integrated OpenStack)
- 2.VMware Datacenter design and deployment with vcenter, NSX, VIO.
- 3. Openstack datacenter lab design and deployment.
- 4. Open network automation platform ONAP deployment on openstack and fix issue.
- 5.Deployment and configuration of Metaswitch Clearwater VNF(sbg/p-cscg, scscf(sprout) on vmware vcenter.
- 6. Integration of Metaswitch with spirent HSS and Homestead.
- 7. Complete ims lab deployment (DNS,ntp,esxi,vcenter,ims node) on vmware cloud.

Ericsson India Ltd
Customer Support Engineer
June 2013 - October 2015 (2 years 5 months)

The PLATFORM on which I have worked with Ericsson.

- MSS/MGW Ericsson APZ 2 12 60/R 13.2/R14.1/R6.3.2.0D
- HLR/RHLR Ericsson AXE810 Switch APZ 2 12 60/ R 13.2
- STP/NPDB/FNR Ericsson AXE810 Switch AZZ 2 12 60/R 13.2
- HSS Ericsson 2011A
- CSCF Ericsson 2011A
- SBG Ericsson 4.0

Nokia Siemens Networks NSS configuration August 2011 - June 2013 (1 year 11 months) Noida Area, India

The PLATFORM which I have worked with Nokia.

- MSS on DX200 and ATCA
- HLR on DX200
- MGW on IPA and ATCA

Ericsson NSS ENGINEER

2009 - 2011 (2 years)

Worked as a Field maintenance engineer in wireless switch in Airtel Meerut location(UPW). This comprises of O&M of many nodes BSS/NSS/HLR/STP/MSS/MGW.

Work Performed as Switch Engineer for Ericsson Wireless MSC (AXE 810)

-- APG, CP fault and RP fault Rectification.

#Configuration of B No. routing plans, charging plans, Short Codes openings, Roaming definitions, GT openings etc.

#Announcement loading.

#Fault Listing and their rectification of cards in MSC, BSC, Media Gateway and their replacement.

#Familiar with all types of Call Testing Scenarios: Pre-Paid, Post-Paid, VAS.

#Responsible for O&M of handover nodes from project. There testing and AT.

#Responsible for Augmentation of Interfaces in Nodes based on utilization.

#Responsible for maintaining KPI of several BSS/NSS nodes.

#Responsible for resolution of POI/Other operator outages.

#Responsible for resolution of GB link/OSS link outages.

#Responsible for Hardware related alarms in Network Nodes.

#Responsible for successful migration of BSS Nodes as per plan provided by DNP.

#Preventive and Corrective Maintenance of MSC/BSC/STP/HLR and other Core Elements.

Education

INSAID

PGP, Data Science and AI · (January 2020 - July 2022)

INSAID

GCDAI, Data science · (2020 - 2020)

University of Rajasthan

Btech, electrconic and communication · (2005 - 2009)